<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Barry Hikes The PCT</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/feeds/all.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><item><title>Castle Rock State Park Training</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/castle-rock-state-park-training.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Friday was my last day at work which means it's time to start my &lt;strong&gt;official&lt;/strong&gt; training.  A friend and I headed up to my favorite hiking spot in the area at Castle Rock State Park.  Our goal was to hike 10 miles with our packs loaded while keeping our pace in mind.  We'd like to be comfortable hiking around 2.5 miles per hour on the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/images/training-3-8.png" data-lightbox="training-crsp" data-title="Training hike map"&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/training-3-8.png"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Training hike map
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wore my REI long sleeved sun shirt that I planned on wearing at the start of the trail.  Unfortunately, there are a couple seams that give me pretty bad pack rash so I'll have to start thinking about alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tree cover at Castle Rock gave me good chance to test my Spot GPS beacon.  It looks like it had trouble picking up signal in a few spots as there are a few markers missing from the map.  This wasn't too surprising as I'd seen this mentioned in reviews before.  I'm still happy with the amount that gets through, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also able to play with the special messages I can send from the Spot.  I have it setup to display a tent icon or a home icon which I plan to use when I'm at a camp site or in town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to stretch our hike out longer than the established trail, we had to add a side route through a residential area.  We didn't realize just how residential it was so we cut our walk short and only made it through 8 miles.  Other than a few hiccups, it was a gorgeous day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0X4z_Os3erM/VPuMcxwmGCI/AAAAAAAADME/HZgjvi86BAM/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150307_112529.jpg" data-lightbox="training-crsp" data-title="Training hike at Castle Rock State Park"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-0X4z_Os3erM/VPuMcxwmGCI/AAAAAAAADME/HZgjvi86BAM/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150307_112529.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Training hike at Castle Rock State Park
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Barry Wainstock</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:bwainstock.github.io,2015-03-07:pelican-skeleton/castle-rock-state-park-training.html</guid></item><item><title>To-Do List</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/to-do-list.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="fa fa-check-square"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Apply for a passport
&lt;br&gt;&lt;span class="fa fa-square-o"&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Get a physical&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Barry Wainstock</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:bwainstock.github.io,2015-03-07:pelican-skeleton/to-do-list.html</guid></item><item><title>Gear Breakdown</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/gear-breakdown.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Living out of a backpack for five months takes some very careful planning.  Everything that you carry on your back should have a purpose, maybe even two or three.  The idea is to keep weight to a minimum while trying to stay comfortable and safe.  I've made a few weight concessions in order to keep my comfort level higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're looking for just a list with weights, check out my &lt;a href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/pages/gear.html"&gt;gear list&lt;/a&gt;.  If you have any questions about anything you do or don't see here, please leave me a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-EHd2CSbT1RY/VPOvQoOeeCI/AAAAAAAADGM/BzpXMUTnlc0/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_163034.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="All packed up."&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-EHd2CSbT1RY/VPOvQoOeeCI/AAAAAAAADGM/BzpXMUTnlc0/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_163034.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        All packed up.
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it stands now, my &lt;strong&gt;base pack weight&lt;/strong&gt; hovers around 15 pounds.  This number includes everything carried in your backpack except for &lt;em&gt;consumables&lt;/em&gt;, which are typically food, water, and fuel.  Many people are able to get their base pack weight to 10 pounds or under, while others are closer to the 20 pound mark.  With all of that said, gear selection is very personal.  There are probably more arguments over gear than there are about gay marriage or taxation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn't get a chance to photograph everything.  Some things I just didn't take a picture of and others I haven't bought yet.  Use your imagination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Big Three&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ONqQJ7n0Us4/VPOlhZu4gYI/AAAAAAAADAE/dfUMEzql8No/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_154905.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="The Big Three/Four"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-ONqQJ7n0Us4/VPOlhZu4gYI/AAAAAAAADAE/dfUMEzql8No/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_154905.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        The Big Three/Four
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
Your backpack, shelter, and sleeping bag are typically the three main contributors to your base pack weight.  I also like to include my sleeping pad in this category as it's a pretty major part of my pack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Backpack&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ULA Circuit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-23EzEb_dGjE/VPOjJw2bilI/AAAAAAAAC90/FqEfu5TM4aQ/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_153832.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="ULA Circuit"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-23EzEb_dGjE/VPOjJw2bilI/AAAAAAAAC90/FqEfu5TM4aQ/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_153832.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        ULA Circuit
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
This bag is extremely popular on the PCT and for good reason.  It's relatively light, has large pockets on the hip belt, and stands up to a beating.  It's fits very comfortably on me and I have no complaints about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Agnes Fly Creek UL2 Tent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another piece of popular PCT gear.  This tent is a great compromise between weight and space.  A big part of choosing a tent for me was finding one with enough space inside.  I like that I am able to fit myself and my bag inside this tent.  I wouldnt' say it's spacious, but it's definately not a tight squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sleeping Bag&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enlightened Equipment Revelation 20° Quilt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-98_b7btdkx0/VPOjdjuphBI/AAAAAAAAC-k/Dr0Te7CYMkc/w1196-h885-no/IMG_20150301_154013.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Enlightened Equipment Revelation 20° Quilt"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-98_b7btdkx0/VPOjdjuphBI/AAAAAAAAC-k/Dr0Te7CYMkc/w1196-h885-no/IMG_20150301_154013.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Enlightened Equipment Revelation 20° Quilt
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
Not a lot of people outside of the through hiker or ultralight backpacking communities are familiar with quilts.  For three season camping, I much prefer this style of sleeping bag because it lets me thermoregulate better.  While a sleeping bag zips up on one side and completely closes, a quilt often times only has a few snap buttons along one edge and no hood.  Because I sleep on the warmer side, this system lets me thermoregulate better.  It also usually means lower weights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sleeping Pad&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Therm-a-Rest NeoAir Xlite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-SYAV07zxumg/VPOkOW4ouUI/AAAAAAAADII/tsYMhog1uYc/w1598-h878-no/IMG_20150301_154322.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Therm-a-Rest NeoAir Xlite"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-SYAV07zxumg/VPOkOW4ouUI/AAAAAAAADII/tsYMhog1uYc/w1598-h878-no/IMG_20150301_154322.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Therm-a-Rest NeoAir Xlite
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
Many hikers take those folding foam sleeping pads on their PCT hike.  For the most part, these pads tend to help with heat loss to the ground, but they don't do much for comfort.  Getting a good night's sleep is extremely critical for hiking 15 to 20 miles per day, so I don't want to cut any corners here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Hydration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ajo77SOZGyg/VPOnJ4Z23SI/AAAAAAAADHo/fLy2O9mwUTA/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_155405.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Hydration"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ajo77SOZGyg/VPOnJ4Z23SI/AAAAAAAADHo/fLy2O9mwUTA/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_155405.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Hydration
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Containers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evernew Water Bladders and Disposable Water Bottles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to have access to plenty of water throughout the 2,650 miles of the Pacific Crest Trail.  This year, more than ever, it's important to be able to carry enough water through the parts of the West Coast plagued by drought.  For me, this means having the ability to carry six liters of water.  In the desert, I'll need to use every one of my bottles along with other disposable bottles I'll buy at markets along the way.  In more northern sections, I'll be able to get away with only carrying one or two liters at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Water Treatment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;AquaMira Chlorine Dioxide Drops&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sawyer Squeeze Mini Filter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to carry all of this water wouldn't mean much if I couldn't drink it.  In order to not contract giardia or other waterborne pathogens, I'll need to treat most of my water throughout the whole trip.  I'll be using AquaMira chlorine dioxide drops to treat most of my water.  This two-part system takes about 30 minutes to start working.  In order to have instant clean water and as a backup to my drops, I'll also carry a Sawyer Mini filter along with it's plunger to clean out any gunk that builds up inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Kitchen&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/IceKvjqEKKKlVDSz-8mIEhf6KCCXdQWXA3US2e1vUwQ=w761-h842-no" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Kitchen"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/IceKvjqEKKKlVDSz-8mIEhf6KCCXdQWXA3US2e1vUwQ=w761-h842-no"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Kitchen
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
Most hikers aren't eating gourmet meals on the trail everynight.  Breakfast is typically a couple meal bars, Poptarts, or even a Snickers.  Instead of lunch, hikers normally graze all day which means smaller, quick snacks like trail mix, tortillas and peanut butter, chips, and Snickers.  Dinner is where most hikers take time to sit down and eat a hot meal.  Still though, this is usually some sort of dehydrated meal like ramen, Knorr sides, Mountain House, or probably just more Snickers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I won't need much more than boiling water to cook my meals, I've chosen to carry a Jetboil all-in-one system.  The pot locks onto to the stove and can boil water in under three minutes.  I'll also carry a long handled spoon to get to the bottom of those deep meal bags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I'll also add a lightweight plastic container and lid if I feel like I need an extra bowl to mix things in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Toiletries&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OPkCO5qaC-o/VPOqG4rouPI/AAAAAAAADHU/cMt-_6anY5s/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_160828.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Toiletries"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-OPkCO5qaC-o/VPOqG4rouPI/AAAAAAAADHU/cMt-_6anY5s/w1138-h842-no/IMG_20150301_160828.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Toiletries
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn't much out of the ordinary here.  That orange thing in the bottom left is an ultralight shovel for digging poop holes.  As part of the "Leave No Trace" philosphy, most hikers dig a big hole before the poop for pretty obvious reasons.  Everything else is pretty self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first aid kit will take some tweaking, but I'll be carrying blister care, chafe prevention, antibiotic ointment, gauze for DIY bandaids, ibuprofen and/or Aleve, and some sort of foot cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Electronics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-18t3S7dEVKE/VPOrU8JBHVI/AAAAAAAADHM/pCE3fWuqr74/w1066-h842-no/IMG_20150301_161346.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Electronics"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-18t3S7dEVKE/VPOrU8JBHVI/AAAAAAAADHM/pCE3fWuqr74/w1066-h842-no/IMG_20150301_161346.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Electronics
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though this trip is very much about getting out into the wilderness and living with less, some electronic devices are necessary.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had originally planned to bring a small point and shoot camera, but my phone takes good enough pictures.  I'll use my &lt;a href="http://www.thestickpic.com/"&gt;StickPic&lt;/a&gt;, which attaches to the end of my trekking pole, as a sort of selfie stick to get better angles.  As well as a camera, my phone will function as my internet access, water report, map, and of course, telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While walking 20 miles per day and listening to the sounds of nature sounds therapeutic, it gets boring at times.  To help with this I'm bringing along a small MP3 player loaded with my favorite music, podcasts, and audiobooks.  I'll be able to refill the memory card when I stop in town.  Using this instead of my phone for music will keep my phone charged for more important uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To charge both the phone and MP3 player on the trail, I'll use a small rechargable battery which I'll charge in towns.  This should get me about two full phone charges just in case I run out of juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SPOT personal locator is a satellite GPS messenger which allows for GPS locating in remote areas.  The device sends a message to SPOT's servers with my location every hour which will be updated on this &lt;a href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/pages/map.html"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; as I go.  The device also allows me to call for an emergency helicopter lift, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Clothing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the majority of the hike, I'll be wearing the same clothing every day.  Depending on the weather, I may trade out a long sleeve shirt for a short sleeve, or shorts for pants.  But for the most part, I'll be wearing the same smelly and dirty clothes for five months, washing them once per week or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Rain/Wind Gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patagonia Houdini Wind Jacket&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Euroschirm Umbrella&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it gets windy or starts to rain, I'll put on my water resistant wind shirt.  I'll also be carrying a reflective umbrella, both to shade myself from the sun and protect against rain.  When I get into the wetter areas of Oregon and Washington, I'll likely add a dedicated rain jacket for extra weather protection.
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OOJIBVtvI_I/VPOtkrHt-AI/AAAAAAAADE4/iEUZe4GvMSo/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_162331.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Rain Gear"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-OOJIBVtvI_I/VPOtkrHt-AI/AAAAAAAADE4/iEUZe4GvMSo/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_162331.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Rain Gear
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Cold Weather Gear&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Montbell Ex Light Down Anorak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beanie and Gloves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the temperatures drop in the evening, I'll need to slip into warmer clothes.  I practically live in this down jacket right now and I love it.  It's extremely lightweight and packs down very small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-GGHpMDIebKw/VPOtTWdeoLI/AAAAAAAADEs/DIPCokwHq9c/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_162221.jpg" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Cold Weather Gear"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-GGHpMDIebKw/VPOtTWdeoLI/AAAAAAAADEs/DIPCokwHq9c/w623-h842-no/IMG_20150301_162221.jpg"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Cold Weather Gear
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Sleeping Clothes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Patagonia Capilene 3 Long Sleeve Shirt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Smartwool Long Johns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wool Socks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to change out of your wet, smelly, dirty hiking clothes and into something cleaner and warmer at night.  This keeps a lot of your dirt and body oils off of your sleeping bag, which helps it keep its insulative properties.  I find it also helps having an evening routine of changing into different clothes to help keep a sense of normality on the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_Eo_xisy1ko1ZmuC-qck0r08Z1GmHHTFIWY013AEgf8=w558-h842-no" data-lightbox="big-three" data-title="Cold Weather Gear"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_Eo_xisy1ko1ZmuC-qck0r08Z1GmHHTFIWY013AEgf8=w558-h842-no"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Cold Weather Gear
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Barry Wainstock</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:bwainstock.github.io,2015-03-01:pelican-skeleton/gear-breakdown.html</guid></item><item><title>The Pacific Crest Trail</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/the-pacific-crest-trail.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Pacific Crest Trail was officially completed in 1993.  The trail crosses over 57 major mountain passes, dips into 19 major canyons, and ambles past more than 1,000 lakes.  Over it's 2,650 miles, the PCT passes through four national monuments, five state park units, six national parks, seven BLM field offices, 25 national forest units and 48 federal wilderness areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trail starts out in the Colorado and Mojave deserts and then mainly follows the Sierra Nevada and Cascade mountain ranges.  After passing through the deserts of Southern California the PCT quickly climbs into the High Sierra.  Many people say that this is their favorite part of the trail and it's not surprising why.  After enduring up to 30 mile stretches without reliable water sources in the desert, snow covered mountains become plentiful, and with them snowmelt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the much improved water situation, the trail weaves past countless crystal blue mountain lakes and even detours up to the highest point in the lower 48 states, Mt. Whitney at 14,494 feet.  Once back down from Mt. Whitney, the trail crosses eight named passes above 11,000 feet, starting with the official highest point on the trail at 13,153 feet, Forester Pass.  The Sierra Nevada ends as the trail passes through Yosemite and Lake Tahoe and the Cascades begin.  Granite gives way to volcanic rock when Mt. Lassen comes into view after which the PCT turns west toward Mt. Shasta and through the Trinity Alps.  California finally comes to an end at Interstate 5 near Siskiyou Summit and the trail enters Oregon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After California's brutal desert and Sierra peaks, Oregon brings both the shortest and the easiest portion to hike.  Passing Ashland to the west, the trail runs directly along the Rim of Crater Lake, then past Bend, the Three Sisters and Mt. Hood near Portland.  The only major elevation change in Oregon is the 3,160 foot drop into the Columbia River Gorge crossing the Columbia River on the awesomely named Bridge of the Gods into Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the trail descends into the Gorge, it climbs right back out in Washington and rounds the base of Mt. Adams.  The terrain turns glacial as Mt. Rainier towers in the distance and the trail enters the North Cascades.  Once through Snoqualmie Pass, the PCT climbs up a deep canyon to a high mountain pass, only to descend another deep canyon and repeat the cycle.  Spotted throughout the alpine land are small towns such as Skykomish and Stehekin.  In this section, it's not uncommon to walk 75 miles without seeing a road or another person without stopping into town.  Wrapping up the adventure, the Pacific Crest Trail passes around Glacier Peak and over the Canadian border into Manning Provincial Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Barry Wainstock</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:bwainstock.github.io,2015-02-28:pelican-skeleton/the-pacific-crest-trail.html</guid></item><item><title>I quit my job yesterday.</title><link>http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/i-quit-my-job-yesterday.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I quit my job yesterday so I could hike the Pacific Crest Trail, which runs over 2,600 miles and connects the Mexican border in Campo, CA to the Canadian border just inside British Columbia, Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan is to leave Campo on April 21 and hike my way through what can be considered five major sections: &lt;strong&gt;Southern California&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;the Sierras&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Northern California&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Oregon&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Washington&lt;/strong&gt;. After the first 45 days and 700 miles and right as we come upon the Sierras, I'll leave the trail for a week for a friend's wedding.  Then, from around the middle of June straight through to the end of September, it'll be back to living out of a backpack stuffed with everything I could need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="post-image"&gt;
    &lt;a href="/images/pct-overview.png" data-lightbox="image-1" data-title="Map by Halfmile"&gt;
        &lt;img src="/images/pct-overview.png"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;div class="image-caption"&gt;
        Map created by &lt;a href="http://www.pctmap.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Halfmile&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Some Pacific Crest Trail Facts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location: California / Oregon / Washington, USA / British Columbia, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Length: 2,663 mi (4,286 km)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time Zone: PST (UTC-8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Southern Terminus: Campo, California&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Northern Terminus: Manning Park, British Columbia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highest Point: Forester Pass, 13,153 ft (4,009 m)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lowest Point: Cascade Locks, 140 ft (43 m)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elevation Change: 420,880 ft (128,284 m)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use: Pedestrian &amp;amp; Equestrian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drinking Tap Water: At your own discretion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other water: Filter it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toilet Paper: Pack it out!  Never Bury it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average Days On-Trail: 140-170&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typical Cost: $1 – $2 per mile.  ($2500-$5000+, not counting equipment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing on this site is extremely helpful to organize a trip like this.  All of the posts I make are just as much help to me as they are interesting for others to read.  I hope to post here as often as possible on the trail.  Internet service is understandably unreliable in the middle of the wilderness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit more about the trail can be found &lt;a href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/the-pacific-crest-trail.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Living out of a backpack for five months requires some specialty gear which you can read &lt;a href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/gear-breakdown.html"&gt;about here&lt;/a&gt;.  I'll be carrying a GPS device which should update &lt;a href="http://bwainstock.github.io/pelican-skeleton/pages/map.html"&gt;this map&lt;/a&gt; in real time, so be sure to check back often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Thanks for reading and please comment.  It's nice to know someone is reading this.&lt;/h5&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Barry Wainstock</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:bwainstock.github.io,2015-02-27:pelican-skeleton/i-quit-my-job-yesterday.html</guid></item></channel></rss>